Guide to the George Mason University Libraries records, 1949-2008
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
George Mason University Libraries records
1949-2008
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
George Mason University Libraries
R0095
110 linear ft.; 214 boxes
The collection includes materials and reports on library planning and operations as well as special projects, programs and events.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the GMU Libraries.
Historical Information
Fenwick Library, the main research library in the GMU Library System, houses most of the libraries' print collections in all disciplines including journals and maps. In addition to the print collections, the library offers resources in microform and electronic formats. Electronic resources include networked and stand-alone CD-ROMs, the libraries' online catalog, a number of databases available through the libraries' membership in various consortia, and Internet access. Reference librarians in Fenwick assist faculty with specific research projects, teach classes about information search strategies and resources, and work with specific academic departments to develop library collections. Fenwick staff also assist students at all levels -- graduate and undergraduate -- as they become more sophisticated library users throughout their careers at GMU.
The Special Collections and Archives Department in Fenwick Library collects, organizes and preserves books and other items of historical or special interest to the GMU Community; scans and digitizes some especially noteworthy materials for research use (available via the Libraries' Web Pages), and provides finding aids for identification and use of special and archival materials.
The Johnson Center Library (JCL) located in the George W. Johnson Center is an electronic gateway library that supports the informational and instructional needs of students, faculty and staff. The JCL provides access to library resources through the world wide web and Mason libraries local area network of resources. The JCL emphasizes teaching library users to use electronic resources. A variety of drop-in instructional classes on library research skills and in using electronic resources are offered. In addition, course related instructional classes are conducted by the liaison librarians for specific subject departments. Course-integrated library instruction has been developed for special populations such as New Century College, Honors Program, and University 100. The Johnson Center Library provides the following collections and services: Adaptive Technology to assist persons with disabilities, circulating Collection of undergraduate foundation materials focusing on multiculturalism, gender studies, technology, and music and education circulating collections (including graduate level). The library also features a core reference collection, curriculum collection, international newspapers, course reserves, instructional classes and media collections and equipment.
The Arlington Campus Library collects materials that support the non-law academic programs offered on the Arlington Campus of George Mason University. Resources cover a wide range of applied social science disciplinary areas, including public policy, public administration, social services, nonprofit management, business, economics and education. In addition to the core reference and circulating collections, the library serves as a depository for European Union documents and houses the University Library's collection of pre-1987 bound journals.
The Mercer Library, on the Prince William Campus, is part of the George Mason University Libraries system and provides full-access to all GMU-owned print and electronic resources. This means researchers have at their disposal, a collection of one million titles and over 250 electronic databases. The Mercer Library collection specializes in the following disciplines: Health and Fitness, Tourism, Administration of Justice, Education, Biodefense, Bioinformatics, and Computer Science.
Scope and Content
The George Mason University Libraries records includes materials and reports on library planning and operations as well as special projects, programs and events. It is divided into eleven series and includes the Library Directors records as well as department records, planning and construction records, reports, meeting minutes, committee records, and policies and procedures. Each series is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically unless otherwise noted. Series one, three, six, seven, eight, and ten have subseries to further divide and make easily accessible the information within.
Series one, Library Director (1958-2001), consists of files created by the Library Director and is divided into six subseries; Scheduled Reports, Library Director 1958-1981, John G. Veenstra, Louella V. Weatherbee, Charlene Hurt, and John G. Zenelis. This series includes annual reports, correspondence and memorandums, and miscellaneous files collected by the Library Director. Scheduled reports 1959-1985 contains annual and monthly reports prepared by the Library Director. The first annual report of the Librarian dates from 1959. The second subseries, Library Director (1958-1981), includes correspondence, grant and project information, and management by objectives (MBOs) for library departments. The John G. Veenstra (1966-1987), series includes correspondence and memorandums many of which are concerning Special Collections and public services. The fourth subseries, Louella V. Weatherbee (1980-1985), contains documents concerning or created by Louella Weatherbee regarding library expansion, departments, and services. The Charlene Hurt (1973-1999) subseries contains the bulk of the Library Director materials. It contains files created by, or concerning, Charlene Hurt, who served as Library Director in the 1980s and 1990s, and includes information on conferences, chronological files, budgets, correspondence, Johnson Center planning, library policies, and weekly calenders. Subseries six, John G. Zenelis (1998-2001), is a short subseries with information on the Library Director search in 1998, memorandums, and a statement by the Librarian from 2001.
Series two, Correspondence and Memos (1960-1999), consists of four boxes of correspondence and memorandums, created by and pertaining to, library employees, library policies, and library departments, from the years 1960 to 1999.
Series three, Reports (1960-2007), is divided into five subseries: Budgets, Reports, Minutes, Publications, Publicity and Research. Subseries one, Budgets (1970-2001), is arranged chronologically and contains annual budgets, requests and updates. Subseries two, Reports (1960-2001), includes annual, monthly, and quarterly reports, consultant reports, surveys, Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) accreditation reports, and self studies. Subseries three, Minutes (1972-2002), includes meeting minutes from division head meetings, faculty senate, graduate council meetings and others. Subseries four, Publications (1964-2007), includes the publications Added Entries, Federal One, Full Text, and Library Notes as well as brochures and other newletters produced by the Library staff. Subseries five, Publicity and Research (1967-1995), contains newspaper and magazine articles featuring the libraries at George Mason and especially the Federal Theatre Project. Research articles focus on library science, professional development, and public relations.
Series four, Committees and Collaborations (1960-2004), consists of records originating from library committees and records concerning collaborations within the University and with other institutions undertaken by the library. This series includes information on the Arlington Campus Library, Campus Wide Information Working group (CWIS), Committee on Committees, Consortium for Continuing Higher Education (CCHENV), Faculty Senate Library Committee, Friends of the Library, the Johnson Center, Liaison Librarian Program task force (LLPTF), Librarians council, Policy and Planning council, Research Planning council, Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS), State Council of Higher Education (SCHEV), Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA), Washington Research Library Consortium (WRLC), and many more.
Series five, Policies and Procedures (1960-2001), includes five boxes of documents on the library handbook, policies, emergency plans, computer and copier procedures and mission statements.
Series six, Buildings (1962-2004), contains building plans, correspondence, and budgets on construction and renovation projects for Fenwick library, the Johnson Center library (also referred to as University Center), Arlington Campus Library, and the Mercer Library at the Prince William Campus. This series is divided into four subseries. Subseries one, Arlington Campus Library (1978-1999), includes the proposal for the Arlington Campus Library (also known as the Metro campus) as well as blueprints featuring the Arlington building and buildings at the Fairfax campus. Subseries two, Fenwick Library (1962-2004), includes building plans, correspondence, proposals and specifications for the Fenwick Library building. Subseries three, Johnson Center (University Center) (1980-1996), includes budgets, building plans, correspondence, planning, proposals and policies relating to the Johnson Center building and library. Subseries four contains documents on the Prince William campus and Mercer Library dating from 1991-1998.
Series seven, Library departments and services (1959-2008), is divided into eight subseries each of which consists of information on a particular department of the library. Subseries one, Catalog and Databases (1979-1995), contains information on the automated library system, and the cataloging department. Subseries two, Circulation (1959-2002), includes manuals and policies for the circulation department. Subseries three, Collection Development (1964-2001) contains acquisitions information, collection development policies, and lists of audiovisual materials in the library. Subseries four, Periodicals (1963-1996), contains information on the periodicals collection. Subseries five, Reference (1976-2000), contains information on the Reference department policies and resources. Subseries six, Other Services (1969-2008), includes material relating to other services the library provides such as workshops and seminars, readings and events, library instruction, and resources. Subseries seven, Exhibits (1955-2007), contains photographs, brochures, publicity, and display materials for exhibits created by and displayed at Fenwick Library. More exhibit material can be found in Series 11 Oversize Material. Subseries eight, Special Collections and Archives (1950-2007), contains information regarding all aspects of the Special Collections and Archives including services, projects, reports, grants, forms, and collection information.
Series eight, Administrative Files (1958-2001), is divided into three subseries: Gifts, Grants, and Personnel. Subseries one, Gifts (1958-1989) contains acknowledgements of gifts received by the library. Subseries two, Grants (1966-1993), includes grant correspondence, proposals, and requests. Subseries three, Personnel (1964-1995), includes faculty information, organization charts, personnel procedures and information on volunteer programs.
Series nine, Miscellaneous (1949-2001), consists of two boxes of miscellaneous correspondence, memorandums, statistics, policies and brochures.
Series ten, Photographs, Audiovisual, Artifacts (1967-1999), includes photographs, audiovisual materials such as VHS and audio cassette tapes, and artifacts including Mason related buttons. It is divided into three subseries. Subseries one, Photographs (1967-1990) includes photographs, contacts sheets, negatives, and slides featuring library staff, as well as, the Fenwick Library and Johnson Center buildings. Subseries two, Audiovisual (1979-1999), includes VHS tapes, an audio cassette tape, a reel to reel tape and a 45rpm record featuring library related seminars and meetings, as well as, information on library technology. Subseries three, Artifacts (1990s), consists of scissors used during the Johnson Center celebration in 1993 and MasonLink buttons.
Series eleven, Oversize (1984-2003), consists of oversize exhibit related material.
Arrangement
Organized into eleven series:
Series 1: Library Director, 1958-2001
Series 2: Correspondence and memos, 1960-1999
Series 3: Reports and publications, 1960-2007
Series 4: Committees and collaborations, 1960-2004
Series 5: Policies and procedures, 1960-2001
Series 6: Buildings, 1962-2004
Series 7: Departments and services, 1959-2008
Series 8: Administrative files, 1958-2001
Series 9: Miscellaneous, 1949-2001
Series 10: Photographs, audiovisual materials, artifacts, 1967-1999
Series 11: Oversize, 1984-2003
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds the George Mason University records.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
George Mason University. Libraries.
Subjects:
Academic libraries--Virginia.
George Mason Universtiy Libraries records
- Series 1: Library Director, 1958-2001
  This series consists of files created by, or collected by, the Library Director. This series is divided into six subseries and is arranged alphabetically, then chronologically. Subseries include scheduled reports, Library director 1958-1981, John G. Veenstra, Louella V. Wetherbee, Charlene Hurt, and John G. Zenelis.
  - Subseries 1.1: Scheduled reports, 1959-1985
    Contains annual and monthly reports prepared by the Library Director.
    - Interim report of the Librarian to the Director, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - First annual report of the Librarian, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annual report of the Librarian, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Annual report of the Librarian, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annual report of the Librarian, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Annual report of the Librarian, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Report of the Librarian, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual report, University libraries, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Annual report, University libraries, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual report, University libraries, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Annual report, 1982 July (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Monthly reports, University library, 1977 May-December (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Monthly reports, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 1.2: Library Director 1958-1981, 1958-1986
    Includes correspondence, grant and project information, and management by objectives (MBOs) for library departments.
    - Administration correspondence Dr. V.H. Dykstra, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Administration correspondence Dr. V.H. Dykstra, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Administration, financial, grants, humanities (Gladstone), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Administration, financial, grants, humanities (Gladstone), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - College catalog lists and correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Federal grant awards, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Federal grant awards, 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Federal work study program, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Federal work study program, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1966 October (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Grant expenses, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Grant expenses, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Grant expenses, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Law school project, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Law school project, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - The library at GMC, one man's view, 1963 Summer (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Management by objective, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Management by objective, acquisition, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Management by objective, administration, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Management by objective, miscellaneous, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Management by objective, North Campus, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Management by objective, Special Collections, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Microfilm ACRL CE 104, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 1.3: John G. Veenstra, 1966-1987
    Includes correspondence and memorandums regarding Special Collections and public services.
    - Administration memorandums, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Audiovisual services transition, 1973-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Copiers, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Deans and directors, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Deans and directors, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Deans and directors, 1980 January-June (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Deans and directors, 1980 December (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - External, Fairfax county water authority, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - External, Library of Congress, 1978-1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - External, Organization of American States (OAS) (Shepard, M) Columbus Memorial Library, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - External, USGS - GMU remote sensing imagery archives, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Five year plan, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Five year projection study, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - George Mason Institute, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Memorial letters, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, 1978-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - NASA, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Old Dominion University, Cynthia B. Duncan, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Public services, bibliographic services, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Public services, carrels, 1976-1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Public services, coin changer, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Public services, circulation, checking-out privileges, 1975-1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Public services, interlibrary loan (ILL), 1966-1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Public services, interlibrary loan (ILL), 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Public services, liaison program, 1975-1983 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      General
    - Public services, liaison programs (German - history - science), 1974-1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Public services, loans to faculty, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Public services, microforms collection, 1976-1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Public services, periodicals, serials, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Public services, periodicals, serials, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Public services, reference department, 1974-1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Public services, reference department, 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Public services, reference department, 1978-1982 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Meeting minutes
    - Public services, scan collection, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Public services, search service, online database, 1979-1983 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Public services, start charts, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Publicity, special activities, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Reception for Dr. and Mrs. John Veenstra, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Invitation
    - Security memorandums, 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Site visits, 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Special Collections, 1978-1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Special Collections, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Special Collections, Correll, Theatre Library Association, 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Special Collections, Federal Theatre Project, 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Special Collections, insurance, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Special Collections, Wolf Trap Foundation, 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Staffing, 1978-1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Tower II (Library III), 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Webster study, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 1.4: Louella V. Weatherbee, 1980-1985
    Contains documents concerning or created by Louella Weatherbee regarding library expansion, departments, and services.
    - Accomplishments, plans and issues, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Report for President Johnson
    - American Association for Higher Education, 1980, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Association of College and Research Library (ACRL), undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Audiovisual planning, AV equipment in modules, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Audiovisual services, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Calendar, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Catalog requirements Committee, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Consult to Venezuela, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Copier agreement, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - External, Inter American Council, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Fenwick program proposal, 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Furniture and equipment, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Grant awards, 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Journal use study, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Library expansion II and III, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Management by objective (MBO), 1979-1982 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Management by objective (MBO), 1979-1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Marymount College cooperation, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Microcomputers, 1981-1983 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Office of Management Studies (OMS), 1981 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Osborne microcomputer, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - RAC systems company, Jerome P. Siok, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - State of the library address, 1983 May 5 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Weekly activities, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 1.5: Charlene Hurt, 1973-1999
    Contains files created by Charlene Hurt including information on conferences, chronological files, budgets, correspondence, Johnson Center planning, and weekly calenders.
    - American Council on Education, higher education and national affairs, 1983-1987 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - American Library Association (ALA), 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Legislative report, Washington office
    - American Library Association (ALA), midwinter conference, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - American Library Association (ALA), Washington, D.C., 1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - American Library Association (ALA), Midwinter meetings, Washington, D.C., 1997 February 14-20 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - American Psychological Association, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Appointments Committee, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Appointments Committee, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - ARL/CAUSE/EDUCOM coalition for networked information, 1996 November 11 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Working together: a seminar for library and IT professionals
    - Art gallery, 1987-1989 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Assessing the need to establish protocols and guidelines regarding in-state access to the myriad files and components available through the internet, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL), fourth national conference, 1986 April 9-12 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL), New York, New York, 1996 November 21-22 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL), conference program, 1997 April 11-14 (Box 10, Folder 14)